<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pathomics | Martijn P.A. Starmans, PhD - PI AI for Integrated Diagnostics (AIID)</title>
    <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/tag/pathomics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://MStarmans91.github.io/tag/pathomics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Pathomics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://MStarmans91.github.io/media/icon_hu08ff99a11f940ac4761bcab7c4c5c317_13983_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Pathomics</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/tag/pathomics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>AI-Based Phenotyping of Soft Tissue Tumors from Histopathology Images</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/saipathomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/saipathomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soft tissue tumors are a heterogeneous group of mesenchymal neoplasms that vary widely in morphology, behavior, and clinical outcome. Accurate phenotyping from histopathology is essential for diagnosis and treatment but remains challenging due to their rarity and diversity. Moreover, current AI models in digital pathology are often trained on narrow disease-specific datasets, limiting their generalizability. There is growing interest in building large foundational models for computational pathology that can capture the spectrum of tumor morphology and be fine-tuned for downstream tasks such as grading, prognosis, or mutation prediction. This project aligns with that vision by focusing on phenotyping based on routine H&amp;amp;E-stained slides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to contribute to the development of a deep learning model for broad phenotyping of soft tissue tumors. The student will work with high-resolution whole slide images, apply or adapt neural architectures for patch-level and slide-level analysis, and experiment with representation learning techniques. Depending on interest, the focus can be narrowed to a subtype (e.g., liposarcomas) or extended to multi-class classification and clustering of phenotypic patterns. The resulting model will form part of a larger framework that can later be fine-tuned for specific clinical outcomes, such as prognosis prediction or therapy response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpi.2024.100368&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpi.2024.100368&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajpath.2023.03.012&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajpath.2023.03.012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karthik Prathaban&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Farhan Akram&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting CTNNB1 S45F Mutation in Desmoid Tumors from H&amp;E-Stained Histopathology Images</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/desmoidpathomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/desmoidpathomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desmoid tumors are rare soft tissue neoplasms that exhibit local invasiveness without metastatic potential. A significant subset of sporadic desmoid tumors harbors activating mutations in the CTNNB1 gene, particularly the S45F mutation, which is associated with higher recurrence risk and poorer response to conservative therapies. Detecting this mutation currently requires molecular assays, which are costly and not always available in resource-limited settings. This project explores the potential of using deep learning to predict S45F mutation status directly from histology images, enabling a scalable screening alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;he aim of this project is to develop and validate a deep learning model that predicts the presence of the CTNNB1 S45F mutation in desmoid tumors from H&amp;amp;E-stained whole slide images. The model will be trained using annotated data with known mutation status and will explore image-based features that correlate with underlying molecular changes. The project will involve data preprocessing, model development (e.g., using convolutional neural networks or vision transformers), and evaluation of predictive performance. This work has the potential to improve personalized decision-making in desmoid tumor management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2023.1206800&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2023.1206800&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejca.2024.114270&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejca.2024.114270&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karthik Prathaban&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Farhan Akram&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
