<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Martijn P.A. Starmans, PhD - AI for Integrated Diagnostics (AIID)</title>
    <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://MStarmans91.github.io/media/icon_hu08ff99a11f940ac4761bcab7c4c5c317_13983_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive deep learning in oncology classification through automated machine learning (AutoML)</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/deepworc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/deepworc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oncology is a major focus of precision medicine, with medical imaging, e.g., Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) and Computed Tomography (CT), gaining an increasingly important role. Artificial Intelligence (AI), particularly deep learning, has made significant advances in developing predictive models from medical imaging. Currently, in medical imaging, AI models are manually constructed through a heuristic trial-and-error process, which suffers various drawbacks (e.g. time consuming, requiring expert knowledge, low reproducibility, sub-optimal performance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this research is to overcome these drawback by developing AutoML methods to automatically optimize model construction per oncological application. You will work on a variety of oncological diseases, with a focus on rare cancers (e.g. sarcoma, primary liver cancer, colorectal cancer, melanoma, glioma), where in each application there is a classification task to be solved. You will have to design a search space of promising deep learning solutions (e.g. CNNs, transformers) and develop an AutoML algorithm to optimize model construction. We aim to make the optimization strategy model- and task-agnostic, such that various deep learning models can be tried, and other tasks besides segmentation such as classification can be used. The project is quite technical: however, the resulting biomarkers can have substantial clinical impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://automl.org/automl/literature-on-neural-architecture-search&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://automl.org/automl/literature-on-neural-architecture-search&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2108.08618&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2108.08618&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/TPAMI.2021.3067763&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1109/TPAMI.2021.3067763&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.erasmusmc.nl/en/research/researchers/klein-stefan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stefan Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis of solid appearing lesions based on MRI and deep learning</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/lai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/lai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differential diagnosis of solid appearing liver lesions (groups of abnormal cells in the liver, either malignant or benign) based on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is one of the most important challenges for abdominal radiologists. Based on their interpretation, patients are referred back with no need for follow-up or they may undergo further analysis with subsequent treatments including surgery or chemotherapy. In current practice, the differential diagnosis of liver lesions is based on subjective and qualitative assessment, relying vastly on the experience of the local radiologist. More objective and quantitative approaches are therefore urgently needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this research is to create a deep learning model for comprehensive liver tumor phenotyping based on MRI. We already have a database of 500 patients from various centers for you to start with four different liver tumors. You first task will be to extend this database by including more patients from the EMC with other liver lesion phenotypes. Using this dataset, you main task is to develop a multi-parametric MRI (e.g. T1, T2, DWI, contrast enhanced T1) deep learning model for the classification of these liver lesions. The main challenge is how to optimally combine the information from the different MRI sequences, while dealing with missing data and substantial heterogeneity. Optionally, we might also want to create a segmentation model, as this is something the radiologists would like to use in the clinic as well to quantify therapy response. You can focus on the more clinical aspects of the project in close collaboration with the radiologists, or the more technical aspects on how to construct such a model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261827&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.10.21261827&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2108.08618&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2108.08618&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maarten Thomeer (Abdominal radiologist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.erasmusmc.nl/en/research/researchers/klein-stefan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stefan Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing the Fairness-performance trade-off of oncological radiomics biomarkers</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/fairness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/fairness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI has revolutionized the development of predictive models in oncology based on medical imaging. However, only a small fraction is actually used in clinical practice. This may be attributed to development focussing on  performance only, which is not sufficient for healthcare. To overcome this gap, I recently worked on the FUTURE-AI guidelines for trustworthy and deployable AI in healthcare (see link 1 below). The first principle of the guidelines, Fairness, currently a hot topic, means that medical AI algorithms should maintain the same performance when applied to similarly situated individuals and subgroups, independent of e.g., sex, ethnicity, and age. While methods have been proposed to ensure algorithmic Fairness, this usually hurts performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to develop a method to optimize the Fairness-performance trade-of of AI classification methods in medical imaging. You will develop generalizable methods, but we will focus on sarcoma on this project. The first step will be to evaluate the Fairness of current biomarkers in sarcoma. Second, you will have to implement various Fairness methods (see link 3 below) in our existing radiomics framework (see link 2 below) to evaluate how these impact Fairness and performance. Third, you will study how automated machine learning can be used to optimize the Fairness-performance trade-off of radiomics biomarkers, and which type of biomarkers are most suitable for this. In this project, we will collaborate with the BCN-AIM lab of the University of Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2109.09658&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2109.09658&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2108.08618&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2108.08618&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1810.01943&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1810.01943&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/bjs.11410&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/bjs.11410&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Douwe Spaanderman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.erasmusmc.nl/en/research/researchers/klein-stefan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stefan Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preoperative prediction of colorectal liver metastases aggressiveness using pathomics</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/crlmpathomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/crlmpathomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prognosis of colorectal liver metastases (CRLM) is highly influenced by the so-called histopathological growth pattern (HGP), i.e. the interaction between the liver and tumor tissue. Patients with more aggressive growth patterns have a far worse prognosis and may benefit from preoperative neo-adjuvant chemotherapy. Unfortunately, the HGP can currently only be determined based on surgery and thus post-operatively. Our clinicians are therefore looking for a pre-operative alternative. Previously, we have already shown that histopathological characteristic of the primary tumor relate to the HGP (link 1 below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this research is to create a deep learning model based on histopathology slides of the primary tumor to predict the CRLM HGP. We will take a two-fold approach: 1) automate the scoring of the characteristics that were previously found to be predictive. This will result in a highly explainable model, but performance might nog be ideal. 2) Take an agnostic approach, where you will use recent advances in AI models for whole slide image representation to train end-to-end models that determines CRLM HGPs directly from the primary tumour image. This project will be conducted in close collaboration with the Department of Surgery, Department of Pathology, TU Eindhoven, and GZA Antwerp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12885-022-09994-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12885-022-09994-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41416-022-01859-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41416-022-01859-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.semcancer.2020.07.002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.semcancer.2020.07.002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://openaccess.thecvf.com/content/CVPR2022/papers/Chen_Scaling_Vision_Transformers_to_Gigapixel_Images_via_Hierarchical_Self-Supervised_Learning_CVPR_2022_paper.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://openaccess.thecvf.com/content/CVPR2022/papers/Chen_Scaling_Vision_Transformers_to_Gigapixel_Images_via_Hierarchical_Self-Supervised_Learning_CVPR_2022_paper.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zhen Qian (Department of Surgery)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mitko Veta (TU Eindhoven)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.erasmusmc.nl/en/research/researchers/klein-stefan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stefan Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A systematic review reporting quality of radiomics research in the diagnosis and prognosis of soft-tissue sarcoma</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/systematic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/systematic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soft tissue tumors (STT) are a rare and complex group of tumors with a broad range of differentiation. All STT subtypes significantly differ in their clinical behavior, aggressiveness, molecular background, and preferred treatments given. In order to guide personalized medicine, identifying biomarkers for patient outcomes is essential. The use of features in radiology imaging (&lt;code&gt;radiomics&lt;/code&gt;) such as CT and MRI can be used to identify such biomarkers. These biomarkers have advantages as they can be retrieved from standard clinical practice, are non-invasive, and can be easily repeated to follow the patient in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to assess the quality of radiomics studies, Lambin et. al. (2017), have developed a quality measurement that evaluates radiomics studies methodology, of which a second version is almost ready. Currently, many applications for radiomics in the diagnosis and prognosis of STT have been devised. However, at this time, an overview and assessment of the radiomics studies on STT has yet to be conducted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we are also developing radiomics methods for STT, it is of high priority to create an in-depth overview of the clinical applications radiomics has been used for in STT. This can guide the field towards relevant clinical questions. Additionally, it is an opportunity to show the field what has already been achieved in recent years, and where the focus should be on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this research is to qualitatively and quantitatively score radiomics studies in soft-tissue sarcoma. Additionally, we would like to create an overview of all the clinical applications for which radiomics has been applied in STT and discuss possible clinical endpoints which should be investigated. Finally, for you, this will be an opportunity to get a (Co-)authorship of an impactful review for radiomics in soft-tissue sarcoma&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21605&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21605&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrclinonc.2017.141&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrclinonc.2017.141&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2108.08618&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2108.08618&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Douwe Spaanderman (PhD Student)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.erasmusmc.nl/en/research/researchers/klein-stefan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stefan Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer-aided Diagnosis for Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors on CT using Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/gist/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/gist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors (GIST) are a complex group of rare tumors with a broad range of differentiation. The subtypes of GIST differ in their clinical behavior, aggressiveness, molecular background, and preferred treatments given. In order to guide personalized medicine, identifying biomarkers for patient outcomes is essential. The use of features in radiology imaging (‘radiomics’) such as CT can be used to identify such biomarkers. These biomarkers have advantages as they can be retrieved from standard clinical practice, are non-invasive, and can be easily repeated to follow the patient in time. Currently, genetic biomarkers such as the KIT mutations are used to stratify patients at risk. We hypothesize that deep learning can detect these genetic biomarkers as well as novel biomarkers from imaging features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this research is to create a deep learning model identifying known biomarkers directly from CT scans, such as specific KIT mutations, as well as identifying novel imaging biomarkers which will let us directly infer patient survival and treatment response. In order to achieve this, we have already collected clinical and imaging data of 1400 GIST patients, in a multi-center setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41572-021-00254-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41572-021-00254-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.humpath.2008.06.025&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.humpath.2008.06.025&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10278-022-00590-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10278-022-00590-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Douwe Spaanderman (PhD Student)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.erasmusmc.nl/en/research/researchers/klein-stefan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stefan Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preoperatieve risicostratificatie voor long metastase bij weke delen tumor met behulp van een radiomics model</title>
      <link>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/sttlung/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://MStarmans91.github.io/project/sttlung/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Note: Unfortunately, only available to Dutch speakers, as you will have to work with Dutch patient data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Achtergrond&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weke delen tumoren omvatten een grote groep van verschillende fenotypes die op alle locaties van het lichaam kunnen optreden. Voor deze tumoren zijn de longen de meest voorkomende locatie van metastase, wat optreedt in 20% van alle maligne weke delen. Het voorkomen van metastase is essentieel omdat de overlevingskans van de patiënt sterk afneemt. Tevens, wanneer er metastase optreedt, is het van groot belang dit zo snel mogelijk in kaart te brengen. Het identificeren van risicopatiënten voor long metastase is daarom essentieel voor het opstellen van het behandelplan en het inplannen van vervolg scans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Op dit moment is het moeilijk te voorspellen welke patiënten met een weke delen tumor een long metastase gaan doormaken. Het fenotype, locatie en tumorgraad kunnen al een hint geven. Zo hebben tumoren in de extremiteiten een grotere kans tot uitzaaiing naar de longen. Dit is hetzelfde geval bij hooggradige tumoren. Ook is de activiteit in de marginale zone van de resectie ook een indicatie voor kans op long metastase. Daarbij denken wij dat beeldkarakteristieken op MRI en/of CT een indicatie kunnen geven op de kans op long metastase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Met deze studie willen we kijken of we een radiomics model kunnen ontwikkelen die de kans op distale longmetastase kan voorspellen. Radiomics is een innovatieve methode waarbij moleculaire informatie wordt gekoppeld aan beeldkarakteristieken. Met deze techniek kan op basis van specifieke beeldkarakteristieken een voorspelling worden gedaan over de aard en progressie van de tumor. Door dit computermodel op basis van MRI- of CT-beelden te ‘leren’ welke patiënten risico lopen op een long metastase hopen we in de toekomst patiënten de meest optimale behandeling te geven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Onderzoeksvraag &amp;amp; Doel&lt;/strong&gt;
Het doel van dit onderzoek is om een radiomics model te ontwikkelen wat op basis van MRI- en/of CT-beelden kan voorspellen of een patiënt met een weke delen tumor risico loopt op een long metastase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Onderzoeksactiviteiten&lt;/strong&gt;
Gedeeltelijke database van patiënten is aanwezig, de resterende patiënten uit het EMC zijn reeds geselecteerd maar de gegevens moeten nog worden verzameld.
Statistische analyse m.b.v. SPSS en/of R: Klinische karakteristieken (Univariate en multivariate analysis), evaluatie radiomicsmodel (ROC-curve, accuracy, sensitivity, specificity, negative predictive value, and positive value).
Goedkeuren van automatisch gegenereerd segmentaties van de tumor en mogelijk intekenen van onbekende segmentatie van tumoren op de MRI- of CT-beelden m.b.v. segmentatiesoftware (ontwikkeld door het Erasmus MC). Tevens is het mogelijk mee te kijken op OK bij complexe operaties en mee te lopen op de poli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21605&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21605&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1097/00000658-199905000-00002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/00000658-199905000-00002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-16-1536&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-16-1536&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Douwe Spaanderman (PhD Student)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martijn Starmans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.erasmusmc.nl/nl-nl/kankerinstituut/patientenzorg/zorgverleners/grunhagen-dirk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dirk Grünhagen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feel free to mail me if you are interested in this project or want more information!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
